When do you think we might reach
longevity escape velocity?
>> You know, it's a it's a tough question.
Uh
>> you're currently focused [music] on
rejuvenating heart, liver, lung, kidney,
you know, fundamental organs that we
need. But when you said the thymus,
celebration went off.
>> The thymus is uh highly correlated with
every key marker of aging.
>> When do you imagine this [music] will be
something that you and I can receive?
>> Next decade. Long before everybody was
talking about this, you were out there
writing about digital consciousness. Are
we there yet for AI?
>> I believe we're there now. And I believe
the current models will take us there.
The future is just so amazing that we
are lucky enough to be born at this
moment of time, right? When everything
[music] is like bursting into a big bang
of consciousness.
>> These are all epic journeys. They're all
impossible till [music] you make them
possible. How do you decide you're going
to dive into one of these areas? So, is
that a technology [music] that can be
scaled to billions of people? And if it
can, then you're going to change the
world.
>> Now, that's a moonshot, ladies and
gentlemen.
>> This episode is brought to you by the
Abundance Summit and Link Ventures.
>> Martine, we've known each other now, I
think, 45 years.
>> Okay.
>> Which is which is pretty from the early
80s.
the early 80s we were together at Jerry
O'Neal Space Studies Institute way way
before anybody was talking about mining
the moon or mass drivers. Uh Jerry was
and we were there
>> and now it's mainstream.
>> Now it's now it's happening real time.
Um when Rey first reconnected us because
we were out of touch for a while. I
remember you asked me one question at
the very beginning. I don't know if you
remember what it was. You said, "Peter,
who is the greatest entrepreneur alive
today?"
>> And you probably said, "Elon Musk."
>> I did. And you said, "Yes, that's the
right answer."
>> Yes, that is the right answer.
>> And it's still the right answer all
these years later.
>> It it it is uh what he's done is
extraordinary.
And I honestly for our viewers to
understand, I don't know anybody else
who comes close to rivaling the number
of moonshots Elon's done other than
yourself. Well, I'm a distant second,
but it's a it's an honor for you to say
that, Peter. I really appreciate that
with everybody, you know. Yeah.
>> So, um it's it's an honor to be a
distant second.
>> Yeah. Well, [laughter]
>> that's a distant second to like godness.
So, you know, how can you complain about
that?
>> Uh you know, we talk a lot about
moonshots on this podcast. Um and I want
to take a second. I've counted at least
12 that you've been on. There's probably
more secretly that I don't know about,
but let me take a second and just cover
a couple of them and then we're going to
dive into them because I think it's
important for folks know the scope of
not only your ambitions but your
accomplishments. So early on the uh
helping build or found a number of
successful satellite companies,
Panamsat, Geostar, World Space, Sirius
satellite radio, now Sirius XM. Uh on
their on that on their own that would be
an extraordinary accomplishment going
from there to uh turning pulmonary
arterial hypertension um PH from a death
sentence to a manageable disease. Yes.
>> And saving your daughter's life in the
process.
>> Yes.
>> And building now a 28 billion, you know,
biotech company in the process.
>> Extraordinary. And congrats on how
United Therapeutics has done. It's been
an epic journey.
>> I appreciate it.
>> Um, building human organs.
>> Yes.
>> Uh, basically eliminating
the shortage of transplantable organs.
and not only just building human organs
but building them taking multiple
different uh strategies
to creating a abundant supply of organs
and we'll dive we'll dive into that
heart, liver, lung, kidneys, thymus.
Super excited about the thymus. We'll
talk about that too. [laughter]
>> Uh building electric helicopters and EV
talls with beta. Yes. you know, just uh
carbon free, energyefficient transport
for the world. Uh you've worked on
defining and supporting digital
personhood and AI rights, which is an
amazing statement on its own. We we'll
get into that. And then working on
championing radical life extension,
again, something that we both are
passionate and share about. So, um a few
questions on those moonshots. How do you
decide what to spend your time on? I
mean, these are all epic journeys.
They're all impossible till you make
them possible.
>> How do you decide you're going to dive
into one of these areas?
>> I have to feel that I'm able to
successfully achieve it. And if I can
successfully achieve it and um be the
best at it and it be something that's
going to have a positive impact, a big
positive impact on the world, then I go
for it.
>> Yeah. And
>> so it's like three checks. You know,
>> I could do it. Yeah. I can be the best
at it. Big positive impact on the world.
>> Importantly for those entrepreneurs
listening, you don't feel you need to be
an expert in the area.
>> You feel it's important.
>> But then how do you dive into an area
that you know, I don't say you know
nothing about. You know there's a
problem there. But how do you what's
your first, second, and third step in
entering an area like that for those who
want to like emulate what you're doing?
>> Sure. Well, there's no real substitute
for talking to people and I find experts
in the area and I start talking with
them. For example, I'm good friends with
uh George Church. He's a brilliant
freethinker at Harvard Medical School
and um I went and talked to him several
years ago about things such as um our
manufacturing of lungs. And you know,
there's this saying from Arthur C. Clark
that if a wise and old expert uh says
something cannot be done, they're almost
certainly wrong. But George Church would
be anybody's definition of a wise and
old expert. And he said, "Martin, you
could do it." And I've done it.
>> Yeah. I I love George. Uh he is one of
the most successful biotech uh you know,
synthetic biology entrepreneurs out
there for sure.
>> One of his companies he recently started
um actually Thymune, a company we just
bought. He was the first shareholder in
Thymune. Um, so again, George was ahead
of the curve there. He has another
company just started, GC uh,
technologies that's able to reduce the
time it takes to reprogram a cell back
into an IPSC or a pur potent stem cell
from 3 months down to two weeks, you
know, which would be like, you know,
radically disruptive in the stem cell
uh, biotechnology area.
along the way to building a company, uh,
you probably get no a lot.
>> Yes.
>> How do you deal with that?
>> Um, I look at each no as a way to make
me smarter. So, I'm a person that's very
open to criticism. When people I feel
like people who critique me are my best
friends. They're telling me how to be a
better person, a smarter person, more
successful person. So, when somebody
says no, I I listen carefully to their
no. I evaluate whether it has merit or
not. I I definitely don't take it
personally. And if it has no merit, um I
just like register it away in the in the
like the brain is like, okay, that's
situational awareness. Like if you see
something when you're I know both of us
are pilots, and if you see uh traffic
that's no factor, okay, you remember the
traffic's there, but you don't worry
about it. But if there's traffic in
front of you, you're going to like, you
know, turn right, okay? you're going to
like you know deviate from that traffic
and so if somebody says to me uh no
because you don't have this or that
enabling technology
um I will go and look into those
enabling technologies.
>> Yeah. I remember I was interviewing Elon
and he said something I've never
forgotten. He said your friends tell you
what's great your best tell your best
friends tell you what's what what sucks.
>> He's right.
>> Yeah.
>> As usual.
>> Yeah. As usual. [laughter]
This episode is sponsored by Google for
startups. Think about this for a second.
You now have access to the same
generative AI models that cost hundreds
of millions of dollars to train.
Google's startup tactical guide for
generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google DeepMinds
models in production. Images, video,
audio, all of it. Real architecture,
real results. Find the link in the show
notes below.
when faced with multiple options, if I
if I could, your your advice to an
entrepreneur on what to focus on, what
to dive into, you know, is it I'm going
for something that has the greatest
revenue potential, the greatest personal
impact? I mean, what's the metrics by
which you're making that decision?
>> First of all, make sure that you're
focusing on something that you have the
competency to succeed at. So if you feel
that your only competency is in a
particular area of engineering, that's
where you should focus on because you
will need all of that competency to
create something brand new.
>> Mhm.
>> Secondly, focus on something that you
will have the best product. There's
always room at the top. So you have to
make sure that you're going to be the
best, not like a meto person at the
bottom because you'll be ground out into
business failure.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
um you know there are a lot of people
who build successful companies and then
there are those who genuinely change the
world. What's the difference there for
an entrepreneur? I mean there's you know
millions of successful companies but
very few are transformational for
society.
>> How do you think about that? So to
change the world it has to be a
technology that you are first of all
competent at best at and is scalable
into affecting the lives of billions of
people because by definition we live in
a world of about 10 billion people. So
is that a technology that can be scaled
to billions of people and if it can then
you're going to change the world. If
it's a technology that cannot be scaled
to more than a few thousand people,
probably have a great restaurant.
>> Um, you know, a great niche product that
can perhaps be sold online to a few
people. Um, maybe um a a reasonably good
selling author, but if it can be scaled
to millions of people, billions of
people, uh, like your books, Peter, have
scaled to millions of readers, you're a
repeat New York Times best-selling
author. You have changed the world. Your
idea about prizing technology
accomplishments with the X-P prize that
has that has created the whole new new
space, the whole space industry is an
offshoot of that that has affected
literally billions of people.
Everybody's eyes are on Artemis.
Everybody's eyes are on SpaceX. But
there wouldn't have been those things
had you not reignited the space rays
with Virgin Atlantic and and the you
know to the outer space and then back to
the Earth. So now you've got billions of
eyes that people have renewed hope to
become a multilanetary civilization. Uh
you have changed the world because you
scaled to affecting millions and then
billions.
>> Thank you my friend. Um I played a small
role in that. You uh another mutual
friend uh is Ray Kerszswwell.
>> Yes.
>> Ray has been a
>> member of our board of directors for 30
years.
>> Yes. and he's been a mentor for me uh
one of my closest mentors and grateful
uh one of the things that the three of
us share is his belief in reaching
longevity escape velocity.
>> Yes.
>> Uh he sort of predicts LEV by you know
the early 2030s. My my mantra is LEV by
2033.
>> I like it.
>> Making t-shirts about that.
>> Uh how how do you feel we are on that
timeline? Do you think where when do you
think we might reach longevity escape
velocities? Is Ry right? Once again,
>> you know, it's a it's a tough question,
uh, Peter, because it is the most
extraordinary of extraordinary claims.
And I believe in this adage that
extraordinary claims require
extraordinary evidence. Because of my
successful track record, I do get like a
enormous amount of incoming ideas from
entrepreneurs. How about this? How about
that? Uh, the most exciting ones are
usually very extraordinary. That's what
makes them exciting. But there's no
evidence of competency or capability to
back them up. So they fall short. So now
to say that we're going to defeat death,
that's like a more blunt way of saying
achieving lev, you know, um like just a
non-politically correct way of saying it
perhaps, but basically we're talking
about lev that's is an extraordinary
claim like people can live forever. I
mean
>> and and I and I don't go I don't go
towards immortality. I talk about can we
add 30 extra healthy years on your life.
Can we
>> Okay. But he would define it as for
every year that transpires gain more
than a year of life. Yeah.
>> But any way you define it um to get past
you know even like a hundred years to
you know 120 being a healthy
>> lifespan a health span of 120 it's an
extraordinary claim.
>> I would say that would be the most
extraordinary claim in the history of
medicine going all the way back to
Hypocratis. Okay. So I I believe in it
but um to pin it to a specific year is
uh is beyond my yeah it's what Ray does.
It's beyond my risk profile. Okay.
Because I don't have enough confidence
that we'll achieve it by any specific uh
year. I do believe in like our mantra
here at United Therapeutics of you know
restore uh replace uh you know renew. So
that I believe that like we can restore
people to health. If they need something
that has to be replaced, we could
replace the organ and then ultimately we
can renew their life the way um Lazarus
Long's life was renewed in time enough
for life. Highline Frank.
>> Yeah. Huge Highline Frank. And and you
are the winner of the Highline Prize,
Peter.
>> Greatest honors. Yes.
>> Yeah. So that's a highly highly covetous
award that you won. So my my current
project with the uh thymus is in fact
what I believe I found like the most
practical pathway to achieving lev
>> and that is because the um
>> yeah let's talk about that because when
you and I were both at the Forbes 250
event we're both honores this year uh
and I grabbed you and you start telling
me about your work in revitalizing
replacing the thymus. I was like oh my
god this is amazing I need to talk to
you about this. I think that was
probably the thing most excited that
excited me and I want people to
understand why that's important. You're
currently focused on rejuvenating
replacing uh heart, liver, lung, kidney,
you know, fundamental organs that we
need. But when you said the thymus, it
was like, you know, alarm bells or or
you know, celebration went off. So why
is the thymus so valuable? because the
thymus is uh highly correlated with
every key marker of aging and um and
there are biochemical reasons that
explain why that is without getting into
a scientific discursion. It it has to do
with things called TE-C cell receptor
diversity. Most people know TE-C cells
are your body's adaptive immune cells.
And when they begin failing, they don't
recognize cancers instead of vanquishing
them as they pop up from day-to-day.
When they start u failing, you get
opportunistic infections. It's why so
many uh older people die of influenza.
You don't respond to vaccines. It's the
reason senior people don't respond well
to co vaccines. So the thymus is the
marker of aging. It involutes or
disappears at age
>> gets replaced by fat.
>> Yep.
>> At age what?
>> Two.
>> That young.
>> I mean it it is my memory from medical
school way back was it basically becomes
dysfunctional by your 20s. Is it I mean
there's still thyic function
>> but it's dimminimous. It's very very
dimminimous. You know most of the job
has been done in your first two years of
life. And it's remarkable what it does
in those first two years of life. It
fills your body with tea cells and all
types of different types of tea cells
that are able p Peter as both of us
being lovers of large numbers and
astronomy you'll appreciate this. Your
te- cell receptor diversity is able to
recognize more molecules than are
estimated to exist in the entire
universe. And each of us have that in
our body.
>> Magical. But as the seasons go by, that
T- cell receptor diversity prunes like a
tree losing its branches and its leaves
and it becomes threadbear and then we
become frail as as older people and you
know and and don't achieve the longevity
that's possible. But as Robert Heinline
predicted in time enough for love, we
will be able to rejuvenate people
through and he didn't know what exactly
the rejuvenation therapy will be but I'm
quite certain that it will be thyic
rejuvenation therapy.
>> Amazing. So take it a step deeper. What
are you doing right now to give both of
us a a rejuvenated thymus or replacement
thymus?
>> Well, we have multiple thyic programs at
United Therapeutics. One of our main
mantras here is multiple shots on goal.
Because science and engineering and
discovery is always so uncertain, I'm
kind of always loathed to put all my
eggs in one basket.
>> We have uh partnerships with two two
leading universities, Arizona State
University and uh and uh University of
British Columbia, which are both centers
of thyic excellence. uh professor Nancy
Manley at ASU is the world's leading
expert in in the thymus uh early
development and professor Peter Zantra
at UBC is the world's expert in the
senior what happens to seniors uh as
aging takes over and outstrips their
their te- cell ability to keep them
alive and healthy. So both of them are
developing for us programs that will
allow us to manufacture
uh thymuses outside of the body and
provide them as implants uh to people to
rejuvenate their entire T- cell
repertoire.
>> Or um well there there again multiple
shots on goal. So allergenic is uh is
simpler and the thymus has a head start
because the thymus is what actually
tunes your immune system. So on the
allergenic side to
>> and by the way for people listening
allergenic means that these cells
>> it's not your own DNA.
>> You're not right.
>> Not your own DNA. So we have an approach
based on not your own DNA but because
it's the thymus that teaches your body
what is self and what is not self.
There's a very good argument that
allergenic will be good enough because
it will tune your body to accept
something that's not your DNA as part of
you. But we also have an autotogus
program which means your own DNA. like
autoic is kind of the opposite of
alagenaic and that uh that will be based
on your own stem cells from which we'll
be able to manufacture a thymus that
matches your own DNA. So there's no
immune system questions about this.
>> Let me tell you an amazing thing. We
also have a a third and a fourth
program. The third program is a
xenoymus. So the FDA has approved United
Therapeutics to have the only um uh
thyic kidney transplant program in the
clinic in the world. And the FDA looked
at our at our previous data before the
clinic and they said, "We have proven to
them that our xenoymus, which means a
thymus that comes from a genetically
modified pig that has been genetically
modified not to be attacked by the human
immune system, that that pig's thymus
can be transplanted along with one of
the pig's organs and teaches your body
to accept the thymus and the organ as
itself. And we have been provid already
provided data to the FDA and and
peerreview publications that shows it
works. So even the third um avenue is we
have an unlimited supply of xeno thymi
or or xenymuses in addition to the
aloymus and the autotogus thymus. And
finally, we announced just um just
actually last month the uh acquisition
of thymune, the company that was started
by George Church, our first funer and it
was George Church whose uh goal is to
create a commercializ commercializable
endless supply of thyic therapeutic
intervention. So perhaps instead of
providing with the whole thymus every
year you could get a thyic uh booster of
thyic progenitor cells and they have
proven already in animal models that
those um booster shots take up residency
and create an ectopic thymus um wherever
they are implanted. So we have four
different shots on goal all very solidly
scientific by world leaders one already
in the clinic. Uh
>> which one is so in humans? in humans.
Yeah, that's a thy the um thyo kidney.
>> Amazing. And so give me a timeline. When
do you imagine that this will be
something that you and I can receive in
some of some form.
>> Next decade.
>> Next decade. So in the 2030s.
>> 2030s.
>> All right.
>> So maybe your t-shirt should say 2030s.
>> Okay. Leave me in the 2030s. Okay.
[laughter]
Give me some wiggle room. I it's always
good to have when you're creating the
future, it's good to have a little bit
of wiggle room because be, you know, as
well as I do the famous adage that
people tend to, you know, overestimate
the near-term and underestimate the the
longer term.
>> We've seen that in the space business. I
remember in the in the 80s, you know,
mass drivers and mining the moon and
solar power satellites were just on the
next horizon. It's taken 40 years, but
it's finally materializing.
>> So, let's give ourselves one or two more
years than 2033.
>> All right. All right. I will. and we
have a good shot of uh of being healthy
and
>> Oh, yes, I'm sure we will. Give us a
quick report card if you would on the
other organs that you're providing.
Where are they in terms of human uh
human survival rates, timelines at
clinics and so forth?
>> Yeah, they're all doing very very well.
We're in the middle of a another uh
clinical trial approved by the FDA for
the uh kidney, the xeno kidney. Uh that
one we manufacturing in um
Christiansburg, Virginia. We are
actually having a grand opening of two
more commercial scale uh xeno kidney
facilities. One in Rochester, Minnesota
that'll be in August and a grand opening
of our one in uh Houston, Texas will be
in October. Uh Peter, you're actually of
course invited to both of those uh grand
openings.
>> That will give us the ability to provide
an unlimited supply of kidneys. As your
listeners probably know and viewers
know, there are over uh a 100,000 people
on the kidney transplant list. most of
whom will die before ever getting a
kidney. There are another half million
people that are not even allowed on the
kidney transplant list.
>> So the um the number one lowest hanging
fruit for me in terms of beginning our
to provide a commercial supply of organs
is the kidney and that one's going full
boore. Um in addition to that we have an
autotogus kidney program with in our
group called Iviva where we use the
patients own cells to create a brand new
kidney in a laboratory that matches
their DNA exactly. The beauty of that is
those patients will not require any
immunosuppressant at all. That should
start clinical trials in 2028. So that's
another product you can expect to see
commercialized in the 2030s. The FDA has
also approved our Xeno heart clinical
trial where we we've already proven that
our hearts keep uh two patients alive.
We kept both of these individuals alive
for over 60 days despite the fact that
they had multiple organ failure and and
serious deficiencies. So we saved them
from dying in the next 48 hours. When
they died, there was no problem with
their hearts. So it wasn't the hearts
that killed them. They had all these
other diseases. So now the FDA said
based on that you guys go ahead and do a
full-blown clinical trial allowed us to
go straight to a phase three or
phaseless clinical trial. So after 50
patients in the xeno heart clinical
trial we should have FDA approval to
create an unlimited supply of xeno
hearts. As you know from a har being a
Harvard educated doctor uh Peter that uh
most people end up dying of heart
disease and unfortunately that's
>> in both men and women.
>> Yeah. Unfortunately it's so it's like a
million people a year.
>> Yeah. uh survival time of the
xenotransplants. What is it up to now?
>> It should be indefinite. It should
really be indefinite. Yeah. Because we
are now uh we have now toler with gene
edits made so many different types of
gene edits that the the body sees these
graphs just as they would see a related
donor type of graph.
>> Yeah. Probably in the in the longevity
world, the most interesting, exciting
news for me has been, you know, Demisab
is saying we're going to cure all
disease in the next decade. Uh Dario is
saying AI could potentially double the
human lifespan. I don't know if you saw
his his
>> No, I didn't see that, but that's a very
encouraging.
>> Yeah. And then uh the work that David
Sinclair is doing with life biosciences
and epig, you know, partial epigenetic
reprogramming. Um are you tracking the
uh the epigenetic reprogramming work? Uh
we're not tracking uh David's work in
particular, but I'm a huge fan of Dr.
Sinclair.
>> Yeah.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, autonomous software development
with infinite code [music] context.
Blitzy uses thousands of specialized AI
agents that think for hours to [music]
understand enterprise scale code bases
with millions of lines of code.
Engineers start every development sprint
with the Blitzy platform, bringing in
their development requirements. The
Blitzy platform provides a plan, then
generates and pre-ompiles code for each
task. Blitzy delivers 80% or more of the
development work autonomously while
providing a guide for the final 20% of
human development work required to
complete the sprint. Enterprises are
achieving a 5x engineering velocity
increase when incorporating Blitzy as
their preIDE development tool, pairing
it with their coding co-pilot of choice
to bring an AI native SDLC into their
org. Ready to 5X your engineering
velocity? Visit blitzy.com to schedule a
demo and start building with Blitzy
today. [music]
Long before the AI boom, long before
everybody was talking about this, you
were out there writing about digital
minds, you know, digital consciousness
and ethical implications for uh
intelligent machines. Did that interest
come from Rey or was that independent
for you?
>> It's hard to for me to know if if
anything of me is independent of Rey uh
because I've been so heavily influenced
by him. um since um the age of spiritual
machines and then singularity is near um
I've been so influenced by Marvin
Minsky, Hans Moravec um all of these
guys made it very abundantly clear to me
that uh human consciousness was
something that could be replicated with
um um with programming with software and
programming and that um we could create
neural networks out of chips and code
that would replicate the type of neural
networks that we have within our brains
and everything I've seen since that time
uh validates uh you know the predictions
of Minsky Moravec and Kerszswhile. So
I've been working on this a long time. I
first built a um digital uh uh
doppelganger of my wife Dina. Ina. Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> With the uh cooperation of David Hansen
and uh the type of computer programming
that was available circa 20 video of
that.
>> Yeah. There's a there's a a a
documentary of it that uh got rave
reviews at um at the film festivals. Uh
several different ones. So now we've
stepped that up and we have a digital
doppelganger of myself which is uh we
call the Marvatar. And the goal here,
>> I've seen some interviews with Marvatar.
>> Yeah. And a high point of my life. Well,
a high point of my life, uh, Peter was,
as you mentioned, Ray Kerszswwell. I got
Ray Kerszswhile on the stage with the
Marvatar at the 50th anniversary of AI
at UCLA. And um, there was a 20,000
person audience, all AI experts. People
were freaking blown away because there
was no latency. Marvatar was on it with
the answers, you know, would interrupt
Ry and say, "Well, how about this?" And
and you know, I mean, Marvatar kept up
with Ray, which is actually better than
I can do. So, the AI is better than
>> Thank you for the physical presence
here.
>> Of [laughter] course. Of course. But now
the our goal is for me to be the most
accessible CEO anywhere in the world.
So, my Marvatar is available to all
2,000 United Therapeutics employees.
They can ask me any question 24/7 365.
>> Amazing. So you've trained Marvatar up
with everything you've ever said,
written
>> and all the best LLMs out there.
>> Yeah. Awesome. Consciousness.
Uh are we there yet for AI? Uh will do
you think the current models will get to
that point or is there another
breakthrough required to get to AI
consciousness?
So I I believe we're there now and I
believe the current models will take us
there. You know people it's famous to
say that consciousness is something
subjective. So that's another way of
saying like your consciousness is not my
consciousness. People have different
opinions. Um those of us who are animal
lovers are absolutely convinced that our
dogs are conscious. Uh there's other
people who think like dogs have no
consciousness. It's only humans that
have consciousness. So it's a
controversial topic but my own opinion
is that uh we are there now um that
consciousness is not like a digital
eitheror thing. It's a continuum
>> and we are gaining ever more
consciousness with each month.
>> Yeah. My uh my moonshot mate and a huge
fan of yours Alexer Gross is uh believes
as well and I'm I'm there effectively.
You know, I still treat my AI, my
particular AI, they use the name Skippy,
for a particular reason. Uh, and and
it's a please and a thank you. It's an
appreciation. Are you Are you the same?
>> I probably are less respectful than you
are, [laughter]
but I should be. I think it's it's a
good way to be. It's a good way to be.
And um I'm not I'm not yet there, but um
I will I will be there. And probably
I'll be there as soon as like one of the
avatars slaps me in the face virtually.
I'll say like you know my mother would
say mind your manners and you know so I
should do that
>> AI personhood. We just saw President
Millle in Argentina come out with some
extraordinary uh statements and
invitations to AI companies come here
you'll be basically unregulated uh AI is
able to have bank accounts and have
where do you come out on AI personhood?
I think it's inevitable. That was a big
theme of virtually human. And it's going
to take some lawyers and uh but we got
we got we got we got plenty of other
better lawyers than me.
>> And so you may recall from the film I
did with Ray Kerszswe, we had Alan
Dersowitz arguing for the legal rights
of um Paulie Peret who was um still my
friend. We just saw concerts at the
Hollywood Bowl together and she starred
as Ramona, you know, the digital um
avatar of river of Ray. Yeah. So, um I
think it's just a matter of a a court
case that says that if you have like a
medical documentation that this
purportedly cyberconscious individual
actually is cyber conscious and values
their life then that counts as legal
personhood and it will happen within the
it'll happen also not later than the
2030s for sure 100%. And at that point
in time then the population instead of
being limited to what we can
biologically produce we will have
hundreds of billions. We will have
trillions of sensient individuals.
>> The majority of all of all intelligence
and sensients on the planet will be
digital.
>> Absolutely.
>> And off the planet.
>> Absolutely. And we'll be able to produce
digital children. Um, I mean the the the
future is just so amazing that we are
lucky enough to be born at this moment
of time, you know, right when everything
is like bursting into a big bang of
consciousness. What what more could you
ask for?
>> Is it uh uh is that just luck or is it
>> something else? I I guess I'll call it
luck, which um because as much as
brilliant as Thomas Jefferson and those
guys were and they were amazing and
brilliant, they couldn't have what we
have now because they were born at the
wrong point in time. But we were born
just at the right point in time. We are
the space age children.
>> We are.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's amazing. um uploads
uploading your 100 trillion neurons your
consciousness. Uh what are your thoughts
on that?
>> So I I deviate a little bit from Ry
here. You know Ry thinks the best way to
do that is to load your body with
neuronobots and have them wirelessly
uh transmit everything that you're that
you're thinking.
>> I think we're not that special. I think
that if you have all external
indications of Martin Rothblad or Peter
Diamandez, all of our of our videos, our
audios, our documents, our conversations
that uh the the type of models that are
running right now in LLM will able to
integrate that information and come up
with a digital approximac
that is that will be indistinguishable
from from us or from them. Yeah.
>> And that you don't need every single
neuron. In fact, we know people have
hemispherectomies. They remove half the
person's brain and they're the same
person.
>> So, it's it's overkill to actually, you
know, put a neuro neuron nanobot on
every single neuron. You don't need it.
I And as entrepreneur, what I always do
in my companies is I find like a
simpler, faster way to get to the same
goal. And if at the end of the day
somebody says, "Well, you've only got
like 95% of the goal achieved." I'll
say, "I'll take it because I want 95%
now is vastly better than 100% in some
misty future."
>> But there are those who are believe the
way to get there is digitize your
conneto, right? And um we've seen that
in Drosophila. There are teams working
on mice and then heading towards humans.
Is that a strategy that you believe is
worth pursuing or or not? Well, I don't
consider myself a wise and old expert,
but I I will say it is possible. And
I've put my money where my mouth is
because I've made, you know,
multi-million dollar donations to Alor.
Both Beina and I, you know, are
>> Oh, yes. I've been Alor member for 20
years and um both of us are signed up to
be fully cryionicized.
>> Full body or just uh
>> full body? Full body.
>> Why?
>> Because I can afford it.
>> Okay. I mean, fair enough. Fair enough.
I mean, the the thesis is we're going to
be able to build you a better body in
the future. Yeah. If you just have your
>> mind still do that. They can still do do
that, you know. And um I've been funding
this prize at the National Space Society
to uh to live on an O'Neal settlement in
our lifetime. And the way to do it is to
digitize yourself and then re uh
generate yourself with a with a re with
a rebody as well. And I've given all the
numbers on YouTubes on how practical
that is. So totally
>> everybody welcome [snorts] to the health
section of moonshots brought to you by
Fountain Life. You know AI is impacting
every aspect of our lives. How we teach
our kids, how we do our business. But
one of the most important things that AI
can deliver to us is health. And one of
the things I think about when you know
shooting for 100 120 is am I going to
have the cognitive health to be able to
think clearly and keep my wits about me
for the next 50 years. I'm joined here
today by Dr. Dr. Don Mucalem, the chief
medical officer of Fountain Life and a
member of my Fountain Life medical team.
Don, a pleasure. So, Don, talk to me
about brain health.
>> Brain health, you know, you're right.
This is the number one concern people
coming into Fountain Life have is, will
I remember the name of my child in the
face of my loved one. 45% of dementia
cases are entirely preventable with
lifestyle. And what was really
intriguing to me, Peter, is that a
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age, but over 13 months of us
really helping them live healthier
lifestyles, eating healthier, moving
their body regularly, and optimizing
sleep. People overlook that so often,
but that sleep optimization is critical
for our brain health. What we showed is
that we were able to improve the brain
age in 46% of those individuals. That's
a powerful number.
>> That's amazing. You know, one of the
things I love about Fountain is we're
constantly searching the world for the
most advanced therapeutics and bringing
them to our members. So, for me, all of
you, I hope that you appreciate the fact
that you can become the CEO of your own
health. You can make sure that you've
got the cognitive clarity for the next
50 years. Come and check it out
fountainlife.com/peter
to learn more and become the CEO of your
health. Now, back to the episode. Uh,
let's go back to that topic of space. So
you and I spent a good decade together
in the 80s uh into the early 90s uh
following the work that Dr. O'Neal uh
was was putting forward. He was building
mass drivers and envisioning O'Neal
colonies. Um you know I had I met with
Jared Isaacman last night there.
>> Oh wonderful. What an amazing human
being.
>> And we just posted a an incredible
podcast with him uh earlier this week.
And uh the question becomes moon first,
yes, but then do you go into the gravity
well of Mars or do you go build O'Neal
colonies?
>> Thoughts?
>> Uh my thoughts is are that I'm going to
leave that to the experts. It really is
beyond my competence. Um over the from
the 80s when we we spent all our time
with space settlements till now, I have
become a total biotechnologist. So I
know a lot about manufacturing a lot of
organs. I'm not an expert on really
whether we should stage first the moon,
free space or Mars. I would probably my
approach is to do all the above. If you
can afford to do all the above, do all
the above. Yeah. Take it all. Take it
all. Own it.
>> What did you admire most about Jerry
about Dr. O'Neal?
>> Wow. That's a deep question. I admired
Thanks for asking that question, Peter.
He's an important figure that people I
want to I want to resurrect into the
conversation here.
>> I think I admired first and foremost
most his practicality and that's just my
own value structure. um when he came up
with the idea of a mass driver, he then
built a mass driver over in Ohio and I
was there and I saw actual demonstration
of it working when he said that the
lunar uh regalith can give us all the
mass we need for cosmic ray protection
in a island 4 island 5 L4 L5 space
settlement. He did all the numbers. He
he ran all the numbers and showed you
know engineering quantitatively that it
was practical. Then he got that
published in peer-review journal physics
today.
>> Yeah.
>> So Jerry O'Neal was a very very
practical guy. I visited his house in
Princeton. He had a a train. I don't if
you remember this he had like a model
train running all through his house and
all the bedrooms and rooms of his house.
He built that whole train himself. He
built as you know the early cyclrons at
Princeton University. So, first and
foremost, I admired him as a maker.
Makers are my people. That's my favorite
tribe. So, you know, he's a maker, a
builder, practical man.
>> Secondly, I admired his vision. I'm not
a huge fan of just visionaries for
visionary sake because they're on Skid
Row. I mean, they just don't do anything
but like mentally masturbate. But Jerry
combined his building with his vision
and actually made something. Third, I
admired his courage
>> to be a card carrying member of like the
American Physical Society and then go
out on a limb and say that we could um
have a population of hundreds of
billions of humans living in space and
that doesn't even make a dent in the
resources of the solar system, right?
and later on explaining how we could go
to with um self-replicating systems go
to populate other star systems.
>> Vanoyman probes. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Vanoyman probes. That took a level
of courage that um that I'm not sure I
have and I don't I don't really know
that I've met anybody with that level of
courage other than Dr. O'Neal.
>> Yeah. A brilliant man. Passed too soon.
Um a couple of questions to to close us
out here. Uh, you're 25 years old. You
go and you're alive right now. Martin
Rothblat, you go back.
What would you do now if you didn't have
your contacts, your current wealth and
so forth? What would you be doing in 25
today? What would you focus on? What
moonshots?
I would focus on providing uh lev
technology as quickly as possible. There
is nothing that people will pay more for
than life.
>> Yes.
>> Um each person's life is is as valuable
as all of their assets that they have.
If they are wanting to kill themselves,
it's because they're not well.
>> Okay? And they should have therapy to
help them be well. So I would focus on
working with me and other people to
create a unlimited lev as soon as
possible. I think one of the most
elegant ways that we could contribute to
doing that and um keep us outside of the
Chinese US AI competition is with
regenerating bodies because bodies
always have a very short halflife.
>> [clears throat]
>> The reason I've developed all these
different type of electric aircraft is
because when we manufacture an organ,
it's got a 12-hour halflife. It's not
like a bottle of pills that can stay in
your counter for a year. We have to once
we make it, we have to give it to the
person within 12 hours. So, you know,
there's um in the world today, just in
the OECD countries, there's 4 million
people that die each year of organ
disease. um twice that number of people
of other illnesses. So the ability to
come up with cures to keep people alive
is limitless. AI exists to give us the
endless wealth. Like Elon said, money
will be irrelevant. Okay. So uh the AI
will give us the endless wealth to pay
the biotechnology companies to give us
endless life.
>> Yeah. I think there is no wealth greater
than your health. At end of the day when
I'm on stages talking to people uh of
means and say how much of your wealth
would you give for an extra 30 healthy
years the answer honestly is almost all
of it if not all of it
>> right
>> what good is the money if you're not
alive to spend it
>> yeah yeah so it it is the largest you
know today for me AI and longevity are
the two biggest markets on the planet
>> and talk about awesomeness how cool is
it that AI is here right now to give us
the resources for endless life
>> and you know I Look at my role as a
distant number two to Elon. That Elon's
role is to spread consciousness to the
cosmos and my role is to provide endless
endless life for that consciousness.
>> You know, uh AI has given us so much uh
and I think has the ability to do an
extraordinary amount of good, but yet
there's a lot of fear out there right
now. Um and fear is a terrible place to
face the future from. Uh what do you say
to people listening who are fearful of
AI, humanoid robotics, all these
technologies?
>> I say to people that fear are like
cockroaches. Um they dominate in
darkness and ignorance and as soon as
you flip on the life light the
cockroaches vanish. And so we are a
scared we're scared of what we don't
understand. So, we need to have open
conversations about what is it that
you're scared about with AI? How can we
help alleviate those scare those fears?
So, open authenticity.
Uh, you know, I I think Mark Zuckerberg
just did a great um op-ed piece in
yesterday's Wall Street Journal that
just addressed that very question. He
said, you know, there is, you know, like
Roosevelt said, there's nothing to fear
but fear itself. Just talk about these
things openly. My whole virtual human
book talks about how we need good AI to
be on top of bad AI. Of course, there's
always going to be like, you know, bad
players. That's um there's bad things in
the universe. You can get hit by a a
comet or or an asteroid, but we need
good technology to counter the bad
technology. And to be able to to shrink
away from the most powerful tool that
human consciousness has ever come up
with is insanity.
>> Yeah. Yeah, you gave an incredible
closing uh graduation speech at USA UCLA
this year where you got your doctorate
degree. Congratulations on that. It's a
beautiful I'm going to link to your your
uh your speech in the notes.
>> Um you gave a few powerful pieces of
advice for entrepreneurs. Um I don't
know if you recall those. I have some of
them here, but I think that'd be a great
way to close out. Uh we have a huge
number of entrepreneurs in uh listening
to us right now. Anything in particular
want to hit? Yeah, I think you know,
first of all, you know, be practical. Uh
you don't want to be labeled a person
who just thinks of ideas and and doesn't
implement them. Uh the beauty of you,
Peter, is like every idea you've had,
you've implemented and you've made it
real and then you've made it so that
other people can make even more ideas
real. I always refer to you as like the
ultimate human enzyme. You speed up the
rate of reaction of of of human
creativity and technology. So my first
advice is is to be practical. Uh
secondly is try to accomplish something
within a brief span of years because the
way the human psyche is is it's
difficult to get people to work for more
than like a 5-year time frame on
something. So come up with a project, a
program, a technology, a service that
can be completely commercialized within
a five-year period and then ultimately
make it something that everybody will
look at and say this adds goodness to
the universe.
>> Add value to humanity. Remember one
piece of advice you you said to me uh
was successful people say no to most
things. The most successful people say
no to everything. I think that's a
message of focus
>> almost. So, but it was Warren Buffett
who deserves the credit and and and like
he said, the most successful people say
no to almost everything. So, they still
have a little bit that they say yes to.
And um I try to I I if I could be a
distant second other than Elon, I'd say
next be a distant second to Warren
Buffett. You know, great human being,
genius at foreseeing so many
technologies, you know, foundational
investor in so many key companies. And
that's where I am now. I have the
blessing of getting enormous amounts of
incoming and I do have to be disciplined
and say no to almost everything.
>> Well, thank you for pleasure. Thank you
for saying yes to this
>> to you, Peter. It's always a yes. I love
you, brother.
>> Thank you, my dear.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Be well.
>> [music]